Preliminary Guide to the Bernhard Knollenberg Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bernhard Knollenberg papers
1923-1972
MS 1017
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
21
Bernhard Knollenberg's papers contain correspondence with historians and historical organizations; articles, books reviews, and notes; typescripts of letters from the colonial period; drafts, manuscripts, and notes for George Washington, the Virginia Period, 1732-1775; Origin of the American Revolution, 1759-1766; Growth of the American Revolution, 1766-1775; and miscellaneous notes.
Knollenberg, Bernhard, 1892-1973
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Received on transfer from Wilmarth Lewis, 1978.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Bernhard Knollenberg was a lawyer, public official, and historian. He was born on November 26, 1892, in Richmond, Indiana. He received the degree of A.B. from Earlham College in 1912. He then moved to Harvard University where he received an A.M. In 1914 and LL.B. in 1916. Knollenberg practiced law in Hawaii, Indiana, Massachusetts, and New York before retiring from it in 1938. For the following six years, he was librarian of Yale University. Between 1943 and 1944, he was senior deputy administrator for the Lend-Lease Administration. He next became a division deputy for the O.S.S. He concluded his public service as U.S. Commissioner of the International Commission for Northwest Atlantic Fisheries, a position he held between 1950 and 1958. Knollenberg devoted the rest of his life to the study of history. He died in Old Lyme, Connecticut, on July 6, 1973.
Scope and Contents
Bernhard Knollenberg's papers contain correspondence with historians and historical organizations; articles, books reviews, and notes; typescripts of letters from the colonial period; drafts, manuscripts, and notes for George Washington, the Virginia Period, 1732-1775; Origin of the American Revolution, 1759-1766; Growth of the American Revolution, 1766-1775; and miscellaneous notes.
Historians; Knollenberg, Bernhard, 1892-1973; Yale University -- Officals and employees
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous letters, Circa 1923-1972 (Box 1)
    - Wilmarth Lewis letters, legal and business, Circa 1944-1964 (Box 1)
    - Alden, John R. (Box 1)
    - Boyd, Julian (Box 1)
    - Bridgewater, Dorothy (Box 1)
    - Bridenbaugh, Carl (Box 1)
    - Chitwood, O. P. (Box 1)
    - Cunliffe, Marcus (Box 1)
    - Shipton, Clifford (Box 1)
    - Franklin, Margaret (Box 1)
    - Freiberg, Malcolm-Massachusetts Historical Society (Box 1)
    - Flexner, James T. (Box 1)
    - Goebel, Julius (Box 1)
    - Grant, Charles (Box 1)
    - Halsband, Robert (Box 1)
    - Harper, Lawrence A.-Historical Statistics (Box 1)
    - Johnson, Herbert A. (Box 1)
    - Jordy, William H. (Box 1)
    - Morgan, Edmund S. (Box 1)
    - Nettels, Curtis (Box 1)
    - Pike, Robert E. (Box 1)
    - Merrill Jensen, D. C. Freeman, Perry Miller (Box 1)
    - Lam, George L. (Box 1)
    - Labaree, Len (Box 1)
    - Seymour, Charles (Box 1)
    - Zobel, Hiller B. (Box 1)
    - Williamsburg, Rhode Island Historical Society, Sheffield City Libraries, South Carolina Archives Department (Box 1)
    - Virginia Historical Society (Box 1)
    - Huntington Library, New York Public Library, Pennsylvania Historical Society, New York Historical Society (Box 1)
    - Public Archives of Canada, Connecticut State Library, Indiana Historical Society, Clements Library (Box 1)
    - Massachusetts Historical Society, Library of Congress (Box 1)
    - John Dickinson Papers, Letters on, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Chester in 1874-notes and mss. (Box 2)
  - Book reviews and correspondence concerning, Circa 1940-1972 (Box 2)
  - Articles or talks with some correspondence concerning (Box 2)
  - Ticonderoga in the Revolution-mss. notes, correspondence, Circa 1941 (Box 2)
  - Bunker Hill Reviewed-mss., notes, and correspondence (Box 2)
  - Adams-Knox Correspondence-photocopies and correspondence concerning (Box 2)
  - Loose articles, speeches (Box 2)
  - Correspondence concerning Washington books, Circa 1940-1960 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 2)
  - George Washington, the Virginia Period, 1732-1775 -notes (Box 3)
  - Copy of Washington and the Revolution (Box 3)
  - Notes on important people
    - Colonial (Box 4)
    - English
      - A-H (Box 4)
      - H-Y (Box 5)
  - Typescript of letters of Samuel Ward (Box 5)
  - Typescript of Thomas Hutchinson correspondence with Knollenberg's notes (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous notes and correspondence (Box 5)
  - Origin of the American Revolution, 1759-1766
    - Mss., publisher's copy (Box 6)
    - Drafts, comments (Box 7)
    - Copy of (Box 7)
    - Notes (Box 8–9)
  - Growth of the American Revolution, 1766-1775
    - Original mss. (Box 10)
    - Drafts, bibliography, notes (Box 11)
    - Notes (Box 12–14)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 15–21)